okay hello and
welcome
everyone this is the 2024 review stream
it's December 20th
2024 welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active
inference this is a recorded in an
archive live stream so please provide us
feedback so we can improve our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we'll follow video etiquette the
live stream head over to active
influence. Institute to start to find
out more and for those in the live chat
we will greatly look forward to your
comments and questions and we'll return
to them at the end of the
stream okay so today in the review
stream as we have done for the two
previous
years we're going to
recap reflect on the streams and video
production of
2024 and preflex to
2025 in other words to take a break from
streaming and documenting and typing
while out there driving through the otim
fields to take a look
back so that we
can be
how and why we want to be in the future
so maybe by way of intro or warmup
Dean where are you at how do you pre-ct
on the
reflect well I honestly Daniel think
that this is probably one of the most
valuable exercises one can can carry out
uh you again you don't have to have been
there
every day that
another another piece of content was um
captured but I do think that being able
to take one of these step back and have
a look at the
entire the entire cycle is it's just
super insightful in terms of my own
learning and I think it's again
something that there is no proxy for you
you either show up on these days and it
you come come away Way smarter or you um
you think you know it all and until you
until you look back and then you go whoa
holy
mackerel so I love doing
this awesome okay let's just jump in
we'll see where where we get to we'll
see where we triangulate we'll see what
else people put in the chat okay so
here's a screenshot on the right side of
the back end organizing of audiovisual
production which is truly something like
see an interesting paper or other shared
note in the
ecosystem find the contact information
for that or those people send them a
templated invite or sometimes a slightly
personalized invite coordinate the date
set up the format that they're
interested in make a row in this table
and then lights camera action end stream
and that's happened now three four 500
times so as the sample size grows on on
this and other
fronts again so much of the looking back
becomes even the more
valuable and this year there were
137 such scenes for which there was also
a behind and a before during
after and we're going to use that
obviously we could just play the 137
videos concatenated with each other and
have a 220 hour whatever it would be
sequence you know we we could uh just
line up every bird in the
ecosystem or we can do something that's
fun and and weaves in the the past and
the present and the future so a few
highlights that I expect we will
enjoy thinking about how this might
go about those 137 videos
one of them was the majority of the
active inference insights episodes that
Darius parvizy Wayne made these were
basically the only video productions in
Institute time that I didn't play a roll
in so that's not the only reason though
uh they're also the most popular video
productions that the Institute has ever
made possibly because of darius's
charming nature and easygoing
conversational style and format but they
they truly were great
sessions
as characteristic as well we had many
fascinating guest streams ranging from
the
the hurried to the Beyond
deliberate we had probably the two
longest streams of my
life like that's a don't hold me to it
but but probably um above 80% on that
the two Mega streams of the
Symposium
and only two paper focused live stream
series with a full.
0.1.2 with the
authors and that was interesting and
different maybe we can
explore uh how that came to be with only
two papers being discussed but over the
previous
three
years we did
56 then dot dot dot question mark
question mark and math art so I'll let
you share what did you see in this
orthogonality and space
between well one of the things that when
we when we do these presentations even
today's review stream
it's it sets itself up as you said we
can line up all the birds we we've got
the bullets
and everything is sort of in nice neat
rows and columns and stuff like that but
one of the things that if you are able
to
internalize the process of active
inferring and and consider
yourself maybe a subject matter
expertise in X and and and be an active
inter infer then the question becomes
okay so what does that mean one of the
metaphors I might suggest is that you
move from just being able to Pivot or
slide or take in each bullet in a in a
sequence and start developing the sort
of 360 degree view that you already have
been afforded even though you don't have
eyes on the back of your head you you're
kind of aware of everything in your
Niche around you at least that's there's
an advantage in not just being stuck
with with the blinders on the math art
of that kind of sets up that 360 degree
potential or policy because it's it's
the way I would describe it is if you
have math at zero or art at
360 and then you have this this ability
to come full circle complete a cycle it
just creates the kind of gapping
situation where going off on tangents
isn't just you know going down rabbit
holes so to speak there there's some
real potential to gain some sense of how
the pattern recognition works why
certain patterns you can take your eyes
off of because you think that they're
going to be stable why others seem to
dissolve and percolate up in completely
other different contexts and you don't
recognize them but us taking this this
potential of holding up to things that
are perceived as being far
apart and not having to necessarily
build a bridge across it but just be
able to say okay so what happens if you
keep an eye on both at once it can it
can um it can change the way you
think yes both at
once it it just makes me sort of think
about the
representations of insect vision being
all compounded and sort of pixelated
when we also have just the minimum of
two eyes with a Unity of perception and
then that even goes outside of our
visual field with just our spatial and
temporal situational
awareness okay let us
begin so the the stream Series in no
particular order just basically
haphazard
so there
were several dozen guest streams ranging
from January up through just a few days
ago again there are interfaces and
tables that you can search for keywords
you could sort by date you can download
the tables you can put them into llms
you can do all sorts of different things
with these um is there any that you
wanted to make a comment on Dean or
maybe I'll pick like one or two to
aspects from here just from this moment
I just picked one and that was one
Diego's um what could come before time
because I really thought he did well
again he's the well he's more than heral
but he uses a lot of hules thinking and
I always I've always found that quite uh
interesting and that brings me to to
another what is the limit question and
which of these guest streams are topical
like the topic of embodied intelligence
which one ask a
question which one present
attention or what what they do just in
the title uh I think some other
highlights I see are whether it's Anna
Pereira or David blumen Robert Warden
John boy seeing the research fellows
before and during their
Fellowship also
uh play guest at the home field and I
think the one that just I'm drawn to in
the moment is the Marshall mcluhan and
project 69 Gest stream 69 with Andrew
mcluhan because it it it was just an
awesome example I think and hope of of
actively inferring seeing what happens
rolling the die there was a last minute
cancellation that otherwise that would
have been number
70 so to but it happened to be 69 it
happened to connect up all of these dots
and and that was the through line that
that I
still I guess that's the
question enjoy and reflect on it and
learn again from with or without Rel
listening yeah you don't necessarily
think these things should just work out
the way they do but when they do
it's it's like oh
okay I'm glad you mentioned D Roberts
because I think he he laid he he's
another good litigator of his his ideas
and he laid out a really good story with
some people who could really you know
shred it his I but they had to sort of
keep an open mind and even though they
asked some good questions he was he was
really comfortable in sort of explaining
what he thought he'd une Earth so I
thought that was really I'm glad you
mentioned Roberts I really liked his too
yeah and also cool to see interns and
just I I hope we can continue with the
contributions of others in the coming
years more and more to curate and invite
broadly and globally And Timely and
relevantly
because we can keep one foot in active
inference through multiple different
ways and still be in triple threat and
pivot and assist and connect and reach
out to people sometimes it's as easy as
just present and then let's see what the
live chat says other times we or they
want to do a little bit more prep to
make sure there's going to be
some um some clips on that rock climbing
face that we're going to go on together
but the guest stream is just a really
unique opportunity for people who like
to think active inference and and then
they run into that Mad Lib they run into
that bar so fun times with the guest
stream
okay live stream so this is sort of the
um the the the one that's named after
itself because they're all live streams
basically but the live stream Seri
itself as mentioned earlier focuses on a
specific paper so when I look at these
two papers that we discussed which were
in the first half of the year working
with Chris Bennett on preparing and
executing the active data selection
information seeking paper which Thomas
par and Carl friston joined for the
discussion of and then in the second
half of the Year leading up to the
Symposium working with Arun n and John
on from pixels to planning scale-free
active inference which Lance D Costa and
Carl friston joined
for these were heavy
papers um every paper is different some
more so and these were really heavy
analytically complex papers in certain
ways and yet in
that ever so delightful active inference
way
people had intuitive grasps and
resonances with them active data
selection whether it's the iade or the
machine learning case is about looking
not just where you know not just where
you don't know but looking where the
Information Gain is going to be the
highest and understanding how is that
structurally set up so that again
sometimes you have the most information
to gain where you simply plainly know
the least but that's not always the case
especially if you're thinking about
scenes that change in time or other
situations so to work with Chris and
really go into okay how how does
Information Gain epistemic value have
similarities and differences from
Maximum
entropy those are some Core Connections
to make in active inference and so to be
able
to climb that hill and and get there and
then come away and now look back on it
is all part of the learning
and then similarly in the from pixels to
planning paper which was possibly one of
the splashier in our field overall this
year it really operationalized a lot of
the developments that have been
happening in multiscale modeling and
connected to the renormalization group
methods which 2 three years ago were not
so much on the table for active
inference at all and now they're being
taken
into and across different domains as
that paper Works through and so for it
to dovetail in the dot to during the
Symposium and just it was great so two
thick papers with a lot of direct and
accessory learning both done with very
mature and diligent colleagues and to
have Carl and a plus one
join both times so great times fun
papers and uh anything to add on that
Dean just just a thank you to all the
people that participated in those
because
um it's it's one thing to write a dense
paper it's another to show up and do
your best and to try and support our
community um and sort of take it off the
off the the bench and and try to be able
to explain it in ways that people who
maybe don't have that same degree of
background might might enter that was
the one thing I took away was they were
they were they weren't numbing down what
they were talking about but they were
also
going to Great Lengths to make sure that
people weren't intimidated by what they
had to say that they they felt that it
was something that they wanted to not to
share but make accessible
thank you yeah it's a a point we we
truly can't make enough which
is I and we are very appreciative to the
all volunteer cast of this show and this
Channel and this institute and ecosystem
largely so for people to write the paper
it is easy to put it in your rearview
mirror meaning put it behind you put
some distance between and never look
back but to add value and promote open
science and to engage with the true
Serendipity and spontaneity of the live
chat and the live stream format and
again there's there I could continue on
this angle but through undergrad and
graduate school I saw so many paper
oriented lab meetings so live stream
format and then guest presentations like
guest stream format good point were
raised amazing points perhaps novel
points perhaps critical points for
reproducibility side insights deep lore
like
incredible dissipate into the
wallpaper never to be seen again so not
that everything needs to be open all the
time but the start streaming and stop
streaming
button gives us that in and
out and so I I'm just really thankful
that that so many people people in the
research area and increasingly in
applications do step into our clean
well-lit place to discuss active
inference and that so many so many
participants in the live really live and
in the followup sort of online discourse
area get to engage with but also like
co-create and even lead lead some of the
research so that's just too epic not to
mention all right there were four round
taes ctly round
taes the last of which being yesterday
but the date's just off by one here so
check those out I I I could have
screenshotted again I I could have put
every picture of every bird we could
have put every frame of every video so
just showing more but showing
less four round tables were great I I
look forward to this quarterly tradition
it's part of how we see nested time
scales from the most tactical and
operational and day-to-day through the
monthly newsletter and the quarterly
Rhythm of the Round Table the annual
rhythms with different cohorts turning
over simposium all these different
things and many more to come so it's
just awesome to to pile these updates
and it is um a learning
experience not unlike a
reflection to feel busy and feel that
progress was made and there's places
where progress wasn't made um windows
that closed and uh or windows that
remain open and yet the inera and the
challenge of actually preparing a
meaningful reflection because it can
feel just like studying history but
those who understand the past control
the
future any
comments All right you sounded it well
okay or stream so this was the three
videos that were looks like in the
beginning of the year in January March
and April 49 2 squ 3 squ
and these streams in different ways
dealt with
organizations two of the three with sent
Janita and Hazel and with nation Nathan
Schneider were from the metov community
so that was really cool to just connect
with our metov colleagues
and again provide a space that's like a
two-way street there's people who are
going to be familiar with
Governor B spaces or not and active
inference or not so all four of those
quadrants are especially in play when we
go outside of the sort of frisen
co-authorship space and and that's where
there's these Sparks that can fly and in
or extreme 7 with Jamie Joyce and John
Ash great discussions again about how in
small and medium and large groups in our
modern synthetic augmented environment
does prediction attention memory all
these cognitive phenomena that from the
research side from the high road side
we're talking about
unifying and what do those look like on
the ground in
today
okay all
right model stream so here in a sort of
counterveiling pattern to the live
streams where there's the 56 over the
previous three years Then followed by
two
here we can see by the numbers that
there were nine model streams over three
years and
then
eight over this year so model
streams and some of this can just be
categorization because each stream only
goes into one category so it's it's it's
just again just remarking on the the way
that the cards did fall not not the way
they could have fallen um the model
streams go over specific models whether
they're active inference specific models
or even a little bit more General like a
PDP partially observable marov decision
process it doesn't have to be explicitly
active inference based but that's how
we're coming towards it
um these streams from the math and the
computer science side add a lot of
primary
material and that secondary material
layer like follow-up questions or just
the order of presentation from these
experts can can get the the much larger
crew who's at the third layer to
understand what these models are about
so for there to be this sort of air of
rigor with
informality and
engaging the technical details and just
seeing how the presentation takes
off and and it's like all on the
modeling
steady hands and then the presentation's
over but we're still there with the
informality and and like that Afterparty
for the model
almost which is like really where the
connections are made and and uh the one
that I would highlight was Rand
Way's work on the value of information
and reward specification which kind of
connects back to the active data
sampling too and just this idea that
well we have
mdps Markov decision processes let's
just say like chess and then we have the
PO mdp like chess with some observation
error that's the partial observability
part and then the idea that we can see
the
pomdp as an
mdp where you're observing an
uncertainty measure and so that connects
a lot of dots with reinforcement
learning and what epistemic value is
it's not epistemic value towards future
pragmatic value it's a separate source
of value and there are situations where
those
vectors cancel each other there's
situations where they're orthogonal to
each other there are situations where
they're doubly
aligned and to be able to really neatly
and concisely
see here not that this is the only way
to frame this but here's how active
inference differs from reinforcement
learning in reinforcement learning you
have utility function you need to coers
or shoehorn epistemic behavioristic
whatever you want to think about into
utility so you can use all different
kinds of mechanism but you only have one
currency that's utility or reward and
you're reinforcing and you're training
on that epistemic value is the second
eye opening that's what makes it
different
having the epistemic and the pragmatic
value in the expected free energy
equation not just coercing the epistemic
into the pragmatic so what a great Point
what an analytical connection to lock in
and also a jumping off point for
thinking more broadly about
modeling how much jumping off do you
think the the authors of these papers
the Afterparty
actually materialize because it's that
emancipation piece that I think is is
really important if if you're using it
as leverage how much of that do you
think
materialized hard to say sometimes
finishing a paper it feels just like
pulling up to the side of a pool and
being exhausted after bringing it over
the finish line but then I think
then there's a rest and then
they push off in how maybe they see
their next research Dimensions
going and and I mean let's let's see
what others think and so on but then
it's it's more like the model streams
are those are those are the those are
the
hardish crystal Parts floating out there
so it there's this sort of like History
of Science like how did how did jacqu
jump off after this paper I think that's
really cool and interesting but for the
other 8 billion people it's about how
they will push off of this
paper okay all right math stream so
there were five math streams the these
were all excellent Richard Sheran is a
participant at The Institute and
prepared for his lab group as uh part of
some of the the completion phases for
his PhD this Tarter on basian mechanics
and sort of
reave that lab meeting presentation on
these streams I think that's a pattern
we could see more and more people going
out doing stuff and then coming back and
giving round two as a DOT one or or some
other
combination with Jonathan gorard in
March this was uh one of the most
watched live streams of the year which
was great to see because we laid out a
lot of connections between Steven
wolfram's Observer Theory and a lot of
what was happening in Act of inference
so there was sort of this like funny
thing where I I just saw again only one
way to see it like this but just there
were conversations like on machine
learning Street Talk between Carl and
Stephen between friston and
walfr then it's like that is a splash
that ripples then there's kind of the
postdoc level
discussion so that's just one like
academic structuring to see it but it
just this is how through time it's like
a zipping
and and an a kneeling of different
research fields and how they
gave a great stream on information and
then Dean one of our favorite colleagues
Toby stclair SMI with the sort of um
live stream
54 this is not 54 followup on his new
structured active inference which both
addresses many critical topics that the
computer science side are thinking a lot
about like how do we do active inference
with apis how do we think about
multimodal interfaces and active
inference all of those questions and the
category Theory and his Charming
ineffable
style any comments on
these
no
okay there were textbook group
activities from February on through I
believe October
um so they were sort of like semi live
streams because they're Live Well they
happen but they don't directly go out to
the YouTube channel but then after the
cohort has finished we flip them all to
open but they're unlisted during the
cohort um not sure why but just don't
don't want to string it along want to
release the full cohort recording at the
end um it's now
been several years since the March 20 22
release of this textbook we await more
and other textbooks in the time to come
but there's something nice about
revisiting a text not just looking for
more and different
but after reading each of these sections
so many times and still finding new
familiarities and new unfamiliar ities
it it
really highlights and and and thinking
about what what is the role of of an
attract text as
attractor text as entry point text as
jumping
off
and how do you think we can well I could
I could add more about the updates on
the group itself
like about sort of the parti ation
Trends but I'm just thinking here you
know what is the role of textbook groups
that sort of learning
pattern in how we how we welcome people
into our yellow learning
circle I think what's really interesting
is is that um you you you'll have more
to say on this than I do because I don't
directly participate in the textbook
group things but if people have a chance
to have conversations with one another
on the same subject I.E this book and
and its contents the is is there a is
there a greater potential to open up
each one of those perspectives to that
360 degree camera view I mean you've
you've gone back and looked at the book
multiple times how many times did it
take you going back for your 360
perspective to to become really
tangible I don't know if it's got more
or less tangible through time okay
[Music]
um this year Andrew Pasa Co co-
facilitated a handful like half of the
meetings so it almost became more
tangible when I see it from the side
and see another and I just think wow he
just laid it down directly that was like
laying down railroad tracks whereas I
just feel like I'm sort of a lightweight
forager leaving a little pheromone Trace
but when when I see another um lay it
out it's really different even if it was
semantically
similar um and then to the 360 that when
when you mention that um you know
360 um makes me think about like a
wedding or an event and then it's like
where where did you come in from or what
Vector did you come in from and some
people volunteer that information other
times it comes out
indirectly but
then if we can have that theory of
group and and realize oh people are
coming they was a
360 that came to here so this this is a
ready willing and able being approached
from multiple sides embodied only and
specifically by the actually
present and for those who weren't there
it just it wasn't that way for them
which is how you can say things are in
general you know it's it's because it's
interesting to me if if um if the
pattern
most people that are that are are are
taking up a text for the first time they
will they will tend to follow the
sequence of the chapters the 360 doesn't
happen until they are able to say okay
what happened at five
o'clock means something different than
chapter five what happened at 2 o'clock
it's now it turns into a question of
Relativity as opposed to okay so I I
completed chapter 5 how did how did that
closure now organized and set up for the
for the next mini loop right on on the
Continuum so it's like there's a bunch
of beads strung together for the first
time engagers whereas the 360
viewer could could quite literally step
in to any chapter and because of their
priors now their their their free
engagements with the book
they you could you could literally go I
could say to Daniel okay uh I'm thinking
about this thing from chapter six and he
and he's already seeing it nested within
the entirety of the book it's just a
question of when does that emerge so
that's the part I find really
interesting
because I'm not anti- text but I I I
also know that most people end up
stopping as you say and things get
yellow after they conclude the
epilogue yeah I guess just briefly to to
kind
of connect that to some of the specifics
of the textbook group as through many
discussions we've come to see it you
know joking about reading it forwards
reading it backwards middle out all that
it's like well chapter 1 and 10 are the
book ends they're like the opening and
the summary then you have the first half
chapter 1 through 5 being in as they
frame it more epistemic and the second
half is more uh application oriented and
it's like zoom into the first half well
you got chapter five with the
neuroscience and reviewing about where
active inference has been applied to the
system that so far has been studied the
most the meleon
neuroanatomy and then you have the ACM
in general in 2 3 4 and then you have
the generative model in four and the
high and the low road in two and three
and then going back to part two there's
the recipe to be begin it then there's
seven and eight continuous and discreet
time and then nine with a data it's like
but if I just had to stare at the 10
chapters I wouldn't have been able to
memorize that but then going into it so
many times just cycling through many
coats of paint many spins of the tech
being okay with not knowing and then
it's kind of like seeing each chapter as
an interface and all of a sudden there
they are all at
once they tend to morph into rules as
you as you gain familiarity and that's
that's why I was always curious when I
ask that I'm always wondering whether
the person who I'm talking to sort of
catches themselves moving from that that
content context as as the as the you
know the the
shorelines and moving into those
conceptual rules-based heris stuff it's
now internalized to me I can go I Can Go
in different places and not lose the
thread
yeah golden thread Golden Ring
okay fourth applied active inference
Symposium so wow what a what a what a
fun ride this one was
um it was in November there was a third
day session that John clippinger LED
while I was blissfully driving away
elsewhere um but on the 13th and the
14th there were these two Mega
sessions let's see here's the first
session um yeah here's the 19 segments
on the first
session the the the pre-recorded ones
were concatenated at the end so that was
like
cool but but the uh the front of house
back of house on the live handoffs was I
mean it's it's fun like if someone
doesn't think it's fun they're probably
right but if they wonder if it's fun I
would recommend that they try these
kinds of things um and then here was the
second session but these were like 12 or
14 hours each so again it was it was
bizarre I I exercised a
ton and just listened and learned a ton
so
and and uh but certainly was in an
altered state
of just learning and being focused but
also very distracted you have a new
definition of how to manage the pinge
yeah I guess just put it into do do a
weekend and then and then I don't know
so it it was awesome I mean again we say
say more but people want to know how
active inference can be app applied and
we coordinate this Symposium and and
seek curious co-organizers to get out in
front for next year let's start in
January or do something amazing for
number five um maybe could you just give
a remark on
how I don't I don't like use the use the
meme of tipping points but I think it's
I think it's really appropriate I
honestly think
that just just getting to that place
of no return and and seeing that things
will continue
to self-organize like there's a huge
element of that you you a role that you
carried in terms of trying to
orchestrate things and that that
people don't necessarily have to know
the details around that but there's also
a huge element that this thing kind of
has an an element of what we talk about
all the time which is a s
self-organizing system and and and
watching something autop
poetically get its act
together um I think is again one of
those one of those opportunities to
learn how
processes there's a there's there's a
certain amount of of hands on to it but
there's also a huge element of hands off
and then it's again playing in that
space that um gives you confidence that
that would be my only com
comment cool yeah that just makes me
think about Carl and the the panel with
Alex aoria and that was like the only
one where there was some technical um
comedy with the with the jumping around
and all this other stuff um and and yet
also it was
very it it it was like they had
co-written mortal Computing and that was
also a a major contribution of the this
year and and uh so it was like it was
kind of like Abott Castello back again
but but it but it was the after party or
something like that so it's it was
awesome okay fun times morph stream so
this was a series that Sarah Hamburg
proposed and did the other two last year
and she did one
stream this was a it's a great topic the
connection of morphological and and
neuromimetic
computation cognition and active
inference and she did an awesome job
with this morph stream and I look
forward to people continuing to add more
Ros
here okay now we get to active inference
insights what what do you want to add
here
well I I did a screen grab of of
of
the it's not ironic I I don't know if
there's been any any Empirical research
done on this but as people are trying to
gain insights they're looking off into
the distance and I want to catch Darius
and his and his great locks something
I'm envious of
staring staring off on the horizon
because I mean bottom line is uh he
stepped up and he he I thought he did a
pretty polish job of of bringing a whole
bunch of people cast of characters into
some sort of coherency so um my my doing
the screen grab here is out of respect
I'm not trying to make make fun of this
because I I do think that there was a uh
a certain amount of learning on the Fly
that that Darius wasn't afraid of
showing the audience and I think that
Miss message came through loud and clear
and I I really appreciated that there's
a certain amount of vulnerability that I
think everybody that wants to get into
this for the first time has to you know
sort of carry into the situation and I
thought he did it without sort of
pandering or or you know acting like
this was overwhelming whatever so good
good
balance I totally agree I think there
there was a really um
prodigious balance between the
preparation that clearly he put in both
in general to upskill in the field get
familiar with the latebreaking changes
in literature and all that and then also
clearly before each specific
interview and yet to do that background
so that he could look off to the side
it's like the anti-
teleprompter is when somebody is
actually put in the
the pref flection put in the the
background so that they can push off of
that
firmness and and also for that moment of
openness and
uncertainty in
linear online time to be something that
people empirically like to listen to so
that's that's an amazing balance and
yeah the guest were great and we had a
little reflection of our own where we
switched positions for that last one but
the rest were just him and the
guests and they were the most watched
videos on our Channel and it's uh
challenging at for for me
to not have the visual because there's
such a visual element so to do it as a
conversation which was his intention
from the beginning was to make
conversation style podcast style not and
here on the left side you'll see this
that's that's challenging because it's
it's big topic so just to have it strung
along it can from an expert's ear make a
lot of sense but but how does that
become enticing and accessible to
somebody who may not know why they're
putting ABC
XYZ and if you a drinking game every
time he looks away just take a sip and
it's it's actually quite
relaxing every time he he humbly brings
up one of his papers or
thoughts don't drive after
that
right um okay art stream so we we're
we're we're starting to Circle we're
starting to to approach math art but
first we're we're stopping in in the
pure math um stream earlier now we're
here in the pure art side again these
these um categorical
distinctions the categorical imperative
their their almost their own form of of
sorting and and like this year starting
the art stream series know saying we're
not going to put order and change in art
into a guest stream we know we can but
what what if we open up an art stream
Avenue what if we had a separate link so
that we could share with our artistic
colleagues to let them know that we have
a lane and a channel and a touch point
for them so that is fun to see a new
series start again we we could just call
we could just number all videos
sequentially or we don't even need to
put numbers on the videos at all so what
what does the numbering really do um all
of these were really interesting the one
just a few weeks ago with Karen kinan
was
fantastic the way that it just Dove it
novelistic and novel just to begin it's
like you open the book and you're right
there you know it's on the street and
this is happening right there it's like
you're in media
res and the way
that
she brought us in media res into this
higher order predictive processing
reading that doesn't deflate or fall
into any other number of sort of
simplistic fallacies or or ways to
constrain the variance and the
open-endedness of literature but just
engage so richly with the material
substrate of the text
and and and um bring in cultures and and
angles that we know we've never seen on
a stream
before and one of the things I really
like her presentation too one of the
things that I kept thinking about as she
was talking was I think most people
think they they get into a
book right like it's it it it draws you
in and and and she she talked a lot
about how it can also it can also free
you free you up so help you get outside
of your
your
patterns which I thought was actually
really quite fascinating so that part of
it
could in my background I was an English
literature teacher and I never had I had
access to the information she provided I
think I would have gone at presenting
literature in some maybe a little more
novel ways so that was a nice
surprise yeah cool
okay math
art starting in only May with math art
stream one and completing the decade in
the 10th month I'll let you take the
first pass on this
well I guess the first thing we should
do is acknowledge our leader uh the the
I don't know if she would be a queen or
she must be higher than some Royal rank
shanon
um is so already enthusiastic and she
really does have this ability to take
that Wishbone moment and not get stuck
at the branching Point like she can take
the whole thing in at once and really
appreciates anybody who's willing to
take back to the risk thing take that
risk and look at things
in a variety of different ways so Hector
uh
Magdalena uh Sonia Sonia came as a as a
guest and again and all of these people
that are trying
to not get cubby hold into there's only
one way of looking at this um it takes a
lot of enthusiasm and it takes a lot of
um it takes a lot of community and I
think that that was one of the most
enjoyable things was when Jim and
shanana and Estelle and when everybody
was sort
of they they just they they they they
made it feel comfortable they made it
feel I'm not a safe space guy but it
they wanted people to take risks and
that
was you I don't I don't put a price on
that I just think it's invaluable
So yeah thank you for that and a great
appreciate the the
facilitation and the the whole buing of
the creative Center of shanon and Hector
and everyone I greatly enjoyed math art
stream 4 with Kirby earner on Dimension
and synergetics because it was like such
a world weave moment for myself and a
learning experience to to see Dimension
from this other way inside and and it
just it it was that multiple ways at
once visualizing the fourth dimension
and it was all about 1 2 3 4 5 and
that's the traditional or at least
mainstream way that people think about
adding dimensions and that's the
computer scientist's data structure and
that's the the the brain bending
question of the fourth dimension
visualized for many and then here's cool
Kirby just like hold the t in your hand
hold the grain of sand in your hand
there's the four it's like what do you
mean there's the four it's like they're
just all all there at once
spatially and here's the math so I think
it's awesome and uh then the a can I say
one thing apologies to Kirby I actually
put this image on this slide in
dedication to him and then completely
forgot to mention his name as you can
see tickles
24d right so yeah uh shout out to Kirby
nice cool cool cool Kirby my my the
closest thing I know to a human
Yoda and then here is uh math art stream
11 the mathematical holiday poetry
party we didn't realize it when it was
planned to be but I was thinking like
you know there's people who have
cancelled
streams weeks before or minutes before
there's times where we've rescheduled
but only Shana has taken the non stream
and turned it into into its own
performance of like this dark like the
stre it hasn't happened but it's like
now especially it has so that's why I
have it sort of like fading because when
we imagine in the in the dark
Imaginarium the in the dark syposium if
we imagine it it's like it it has been
because it hasn't but it hasn't because
it has only been imagined and so when
when we're playing with so many things
about what what what is cognitive and
real and embodied and all these it's
it's just a a symbolic T to force and
again for most people they just like
cancel and that's kind of the the it and
the all but but even a cancellation goes
further okay okay active infer an stream
I'll let you take the first path on this
no I I I can't make any passes my my
putting these two images on here is
because the uh the shift e eyes on the
ant that's the extent of it most of the
stuff you talk about I have no clue what
the heck you're
doing yeah well this also began I guess
just four months
ago but I've really treasured it as an
opportunity to give like a little
topical
slice into some development
effort also heavily using cursor and
llms and code and all of
that and I I I try to leave it all out
on the Dance Floor I try to bring in the
the Deep baseball history and references
and Skip
around um I I I hope it's enjoyable and
kind of like a variety
show with with all shinier when you've
left than when you were
wrong it's it's it's super funny and
and a a a topic that we always come back
to with okay their subject matter
expertise and what and just seeing like
literally over these streams you'll see
even in the 67 eight and I'm saying it's
doing 800 lines but 200 lines was the
limit just a few months ago so being
there when the tide pulls out and the
100 foot wave comes onto Shore and being
like no the subject matter expertise and
the cramming textbooks of basian
Statistics into your head and the coding
and the for loops and all of these it's
like that's
not going to fall onto a human's
shoulders in most cases
anymore so as that as that knowledge
playground just morphs I mean these
these may be seen as some of the most
rapid months of synthetic intelligence
acceleration in a long time yes in a
10,000 or 100,000 year can you say that
in history like it's it's we're the
you're on the almost vertical like I I I
think there's the there's the sort of
fractally element of zooming in and it
being a hockey stick Oh Canada um all
the way but at the same time just just
talk about seeing it play out on the
daytoday with the new versions of cursor
and the new language
models and and the the fixating
salience of the sophistication of the
technology and like the kind of
Promethean angle on that and the the the
power and the potential and open source
and
revisiting a bunch of previous papers
that that I've
written qualitative ones collaborations
more structural
ones kicking it off with the field shift
just saying hey you know it it's not
necessarily you might not give an A+ but
at the at the B+ to a level we have the
all by all maps like the sphere of the
shifted like you could think about a in
terms of B it's like okay well now we
have a through z by A through Z so now
that the the board has been sketched
and that that's just like it's daunting
but it's
empowering but it's terrifying and it's
also exciting and so what does it mean
you know when when careers were made on
what if we thought about a like
B and now we
have that low bar Rising
tide will will it float all boats and
and what is going to get swept away when
that technique becomes increasingly
powerful do someone who has zero
experience with what how you play with
each of these different tools the thing
that the metaphor that keeps running in
my mind is it's not a roller coaster
that's already been set up in the field
it's it's quite
literally the rails of the roller
coaster are only about developed only
about 10 ft in front of you and it looks
like you're going to go off the rails
and
just you know fall to your death but it
just seems like there's more rail as you
progress there's more rail literally
materializing as you move down the
tracks and so yes that is
terrifying yeah that's that's all I'm
gonna say yeah and just the who's on
first
dialogue light
Motif
just being funny and information Laden
for me and maybe for others but but
again just pointing more broadly like
whatever cultural vehicle or format you
want information
in that that roller coaster is going to
take that turn in the next 10 seconds
you know the book is there it's
static and there's there's so much to be
said for all of that too in the shared
reference point of the text like we were
exploring earlier but when when the book
is
morphing second to Second you can flip
back to a page it was like wait I just
was like it's like it's already
different enough when the text is static
and and it's like being on a on a hyper
mutating trampoline so so seeing that
happen and just it it it just how how
quickly we've gone from here's a great
blog post you might want to check it out
they use this cool metaphor to like I'm
75 prompts deep like wired into this
alternative reality
game but I'm also getting this like
tacit understanding of basy and
statistics is
like you know will will again just
speaking personally will I have come to
see will I come to
see the hours with the organic chemistry
book in the library in those years
as creating the
foundation of habits and
ways that become
empowered will those study methods and
ways be misleading or
worse it is it something that others
just analogously would want to engage in
for like the character building or for
the
traditionalism or is it just like a
historical Legacy cope and and new
nestmates will do things that will just
completely you know it's and it's
probably some of all of that it's just
that it's it's evolved so much and I
don't feel like I've been studying it
that long but I can't
even the there's no ven diagram some
days
between when I finished undergrad in
2014 and how I was studying and where it
got to this
year so here's a question for you like a
couple of years ago 2022
2021 we spent a lot of time in the
Institute pondering this idea that it
just seemed like markof blankets were
arbitrary but because I some programming
in the previous decade I had equated
markof blanket and where where they're
placed with the idea of so what's good
enough it's not just arbitrary it's I
don't want to get caught up in recursive
Loop comedic outcomes aside I know who's
on
First and that's good enough for me like
I don't have to sit there and
continually ask prompt after prompt
after prompt right so where do you think
this idea that a lot of stuff that we do
know now about active inference where is
it going to um bump up against this idea
that a lot of information now is going
to be synthesized through these llms but
not knowing what the lm's definition of
good enough is relative to our
own yeah that's a question to revisit it
just makes me think of of the hand on
the page and there's this this chain of
continuity materially from like the ink
of the printing press on through your
fingertips and and neurons and glea so
there's like this material chain and
then now it's like we have a whole team
of
telephone between the whole Library
and us at the
terminal so there's so
much
obscuris and yes with open source models
we can look a little bit under the hood
and all of that but like just do a
single dimensional linear aggression and
check how interpretable that one is and
then use that to for a gut check for
what kinds of
interpretability in in the short and
maybe even longer term we can even
expect from these massive systems with
with billions of components and
numerical representations of meaning all
of that and and so there's just so much
space
between that it almost like obsoletes
the concept of space
between because it becomes its own place
to
be and I I guess how can we see that as
just the new water that we're in
um uhhuh and and but but but again just
like we we should add the um the car
meme swerving off the
freeway but that's going to be
like yeah that's that's going to be the
the
the the
educational question like when I see
educational organizations grappling with
WEA using
at this level or that level is
augmenting learning or a referral to
student judicial
Affairs it's like that that that there's
going to be a Chasm growing that that is
is not going to get taped over
simply well 10 years ago I had people
that were coming to me and insisting
that I impose rubrics and I 10 years ago
I said those are already
they've lost their shelf life and I
think everything that you just pointed
out confirms that anybody that's still
in that way of thinking
um if if you believe that that's it the
way that you you measure and qualify
what good enough
is think think again it's it's that
isn't going to help you anymore so cool
okay last
moments so we have of course one review
stream this year happening right now and
so I'll bring in a William Blake quote
and then you can convey what you
added eternity is in love with the
Productions of
time what so I just as where so so where
does that where does that
where does the time that's then
processed okay so and now behind us then
fit in to the idea the concept of scale
free because Blake I'm sure you you're
you're the Blake expert when when when
Blake was Unshackled from the asks and
the tasks that he had to do to put food
on his
table how would you suggest he looked
back on is
day or he broke out the quill and and
said something
profound
yeah well what what a what a big
question to to
explore
the multiple of his Works deal with this
in media res realization of
fragmentation through memory of a prior
State and the the
instantaneous Primal recognition of
temporality and time
boundness which is time as produced the
Productions of
time which whether you apprehend this
through through reason Faith Axiom
principle
framework it comes from eternity of
Eternity and so this
aphorism it
it captures that like there's The
Eternity of
the sentences all meanings at once the
sentence as one at
once and then there's the the line near
sequential Productions of time and the
letters in their ordering and the words
in their ordering and uh it it uh so how
did
he
see the end of his day that's an
interesting question after after what
what by by many modern standards would
be
grueling extremely challenging
repetitive
etching work it's an interesting
question when I first saw this I thought
to myself okay so here here we go again
we've
got a highly respected thinker and he's
essentially in his own words saying well
there is a an eternity capacity a caring
capacity a scale free component and then
there's a scale friendly component right
the cycle of the day is is
done when I'm having my own little
moment now to go okay was I productive
today I wonder what what what he fits
into the well here's the here's the
here's the things I made but here's the
here's the new ideas that I'm I'm still
I'm still forming and hoping to to to
bring into
a a way of getting others to maybe
go
long
yeah from from the production of etching
and ready to slip and and shanana talked
about memory and and Hector and sleep
and how you have to remember to be able
to fall asleep um and then also here's
just this is from uh Uncle John's Band
by The Grateful Dead But the last line
there where does the time go it's like
yeah okay if it flies like from or to
where or is it just all at
once that's the sort of time Crystal
time Diamond spatialization of time but
spatial as a metaphor for moments
existing but what would it even mean to
exist quote at once when you're talking
about something that
changes
okay last one
so yours alone
loan well I think in 2025 something
interesting is going to happen and
I rather than taking all of the items on
this slide and somehow being able to
insert them into
a a prompt field in an
llm maybe that's possible now like I
said I I don't know I don't know how you
put I know how you string words together
in a prompt field but I don't know what
would happen if you put in a Clydesdale
a Radio Flyer wagon a a king's coach a
miniature
horse a
table
um two
two tangental sandwiches and a list what
it what it would come up with but I I
think an active infer if I said to an
active infer
rearrange this reformat
this take this and make it a make it a
make it your self-organize it into your
coherency and
then and then if you want
to give us a narrative but just go
through a process of acting and
inferring without without you know I
don't know how many times you have to re
resubmit the
prompts but I I I know that
it's it that's an exercise this is a
different kind of exercise because it's
taking information and and allowing
person who sees it to reformat it and I
think that that's something that's going
to come to the
four within the ACT I hope it's going to
come to the FL within the active
inference community and the the next
count calendar year because I think this
is a this is an ability and affordance
that we
have to take
seeming pieces of of information and not
just get stuck in the the sequential of
it there's there's that there is
that but there's also this other way of
being able to look at things and I think
together that's the potential of not
being replaced
by AI but actually having it act as a
tool in in the context of having this
other way of being able to look at
information and not necessarily have to
continually give it more more definition
more terms
more refinement it's it's literally an
opening up the option is yours like if I
said to you Daniel play with this and
decide whether the where the list stays
where it is or whether you take a word
like subjective subjec and put put put
it over the miniature horse
or which is which is the active
inference which is the instrumental like
it's actually fun you there's nobody
telling you how the puzzle gets
completed it's the actual process of
doing the
self-organization that's that creates
the narrative and the generative model
that you want to
carry into this next year so that's why
I put this on here because I think
that's the preflex moment that you know
four years and now year number five as
you mentioned before we came live here I
think we have that opposable digit
moment and uh rather than being taken
out by Ai and learning I think it's
now it just seems like the the moment of
sensitivity where we can take this other
way and and put the two of put the two
together wow okay I'm going to read a
timely question from the chat and I
think you'll have a a take on this one
Monty wrote how does active inference
explain the bunny rabbit interpretation
uh
with the duck is with the rabbit that's
how active inference explains it it's as
you as as
you uh change swap perspective and
foreground and background the what the
what active inference explains to us is
that it's the fact that our our ability
to
cohere take the duck and the rabbit and
see them as width not necessarily one
before the other that's one of the great
um powers of being able to not get stuck
just in subject matter expertise but be
able to
predict not just the limitations but
also the leveraging
points yeah so if we see time as Moment
by moment which is the the the
commentary for the baseball game it's a
duck no it's no it's a bird it's a plane
no it's a duck it's a rabbit then and
then and then that's how next steps
occur in contrast we have eternity which
is multiple moments at once and there
space between we have duck with rabbit
and the duck with rabbit is in love with
the production of the
experience of duck than
rabbit
yeah yeah and that and again first that
just that may sound to people like what
the heck are they talking about but
again if you can relax your grip on know
it's a duck know it's a rabbit know it's
like if you can let go of
ore even if it's just for a little bit
and just kind of go okay well I don't
see a duck rabbit or I don't see a a
Ruck or a dabbit that's okay because
you're still able to see the
all aspect of that
in addition to the oh now it's a duck
now it's a r
nice horse by Duck Rabbit by
horse there we go but so one of the one
of the critical things here I think is
that I think a lot of people will go oh
we live in a world of of hyper trucks
now no it's still a minimum of two if
we're talking about the the the natural
component of this and not just the
technology olog if we're talking about
the real and the instrumental so again
um I I just think that 2025 that
opposing digit metaphor is going to
really come into play here okay just
copying this in we we can come to
closure but just Monty wrote um what is
driving this change of
perspective the solidification of
recognition reminds me of the process of
gaining hand Independence in piano
um well I I guess that depends on on the
person I mean there's going to be some
people that are going to be doing it out
of a sense of fear be some people that
want to be just curiosity they just want
to try perspective swapping because
maybe they're feeling like they're in a
bit of a rut in the you know the one
size fits all view that they've carried
forward for whatever length of time I
mean but there's almost infinite reasons
why but I think the idea in in a world
where it appears that a lot of
the choices are being taken away there's
always a re a reaction to that and
people will want
to if there's a way to option
up and not not have something make them
feel as
though they're no longer relevant so
last question Monty asks is will the
final answer to the fundamental
driver no it's just relative to the what
you can and can't
do do you have any closing
comments again I I can't I
can't I can't pound the table enough and
hard enough to say if if
you if you sometimes don't want to
participate in one of these exercises
because you weren't there for everything
um you're you're kind of missing the
value in it I I would suggest that this
year I was actually physically present
for 18 to 20% of the stuff that went on
and I got a chance to because of the
nature of the the availability in in the
library of videos go back and look at
another 60% and there's at least 22%
that I have no idea what what went on
but I still like to come here because it
it gives you that sense to step
back um so I hope people that are on the
Discord I hope people that are in the
community I would like to see this sort
of exercise be something that became
more of a I guess there's some way that
we have to digitally feed people because
if we could get them all into a big uh
smorgus board and feed them while we
were doing this we could probably get
more people in this in this room but I I
just think it's a I think it's a really
valuable exercise and I hope other
people want to join with you on this
next year thank you I'd like to
acknowledge upcycle Club making a gift
to us he said thank you for all the hard
work and also
Jeff so what a stream what a year thank
you all see you next time thanks Danel